A Guide to the Film collection FA466
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Ford Foundation, 6; Except where noted, the Ford Foundation films are only available on the original film format
  - The Common Good: Social Welfare and the American Future, 1990; Sound, Color, 19 minutes. (Reel AV 2019)
    This film is based on the report and reccommendations of the Ford Foundation project on socil welfare and the American Future. The documentary offeres new ways to think about child care, welfare, the working poor, displaced workers, healthcare, the ederly, addiction issues and homelessness. It was produced for the Ford Foundation by Dick Young Productions, Ltd. New York City. Copyright 1990, Dick Young.
  - Communication and the Judge, Sound, Black & white, 5 minutes. (Reel AV 1882)
    Dramatized examples of courtroom behavior and communication, targeted at students of the California College of Trial Judges. Produced at UCLA for Los Angeles County, by the California College of Trial Judges.
  - Community Leadership Institute, 1953 July; Sound, Color/Black & white, 30 minutes (Reel AV 1806)
    Film report by the Fund for Adult Education, of the Ford Foundation, about an experiment in designing and supporting community leaders. 275 local leaders from all over the United States were invited for a two-week retreat of workshops and discussions on resolving community issues, communication tools, local resources, and other topics. Narrated by John Vacca, the delegate from Odessa, Texas. Filmed at Bigwin Inn in Ontario, Canada.
  - Continental Classroom: Nuclear Rhythms, Sound, Black & white, 30 minutes. (Reel AV 1846)
    An introduction to the Continental Classroom film series and its early research in educational TV programming and satellite education. An initial summary of pilot programs precedes Episode 147 of the series,"Nuclear Rhythms", with Dr. Felix Bloch (director of the Manhattan Project). The series was funded by the Ford Foundation, Standard Oil Company of California, the Fund for the Advancement of Education, and many others. Produced by NBC and the American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education.
  - See It Now: A Conversation with Dr. J. Robert Oppenheimer, 1955 January 4; Sound, Black & white, 47 minutes. (Reel AV 1893)
    An episode of Edward R. Murrow's"See It Now" broadcast featuring a discussion with Dr. J. Robert Oppenheimer, director of the Institute for Advanced Study. Murrow and Oppenheimer discuss the history of the Institute, its current fellows and projects, and its goals for the future in technology and science. Filmed 1955 January 4, this film is an extended version of the original aired broadcast (re-released for college and university use).
  - Cotton, Sound, Black & white, 4 minutes. (Reel AV 1975)
    Footage of Paul Miller and the Board of Central Rose Memorial Hospital accepting a grant from the Ford Foundation for a hospital expansion program. The film also includes footage of hospital rooms, nurses and patients, hospital exterior, and architectural drawing of "addition" to the Central Rose Memorial Hospital.
  - Coulomb Force Constant, Sound, Black & white, 34 minutes. (Reel AV 1989)
    An educational film about the Coulomb Force Constant funded by the National Science Foundation, Alfred P. Sloan Foundation and Ford Foundation as part of its course in physics for secondary schools.
  - Counting Electrical Charges in Motion, 1960; Sound, Black & white, 11 minutes. (Reel AV 1852)
    An educational short film featuring Dr. James S. Strickland. Funded by the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, the National Science Foundation, and the Ford Foundation. Produced by Educational Resources for the Physical Science Study Committee, as part of their course in physics.
  - Definite and Multiple Proportions, 1960; Sound, Black & white, 30 minutes. (Reel AV 1791)
    An educational short film featuring Professor Robert C.C. St. George, Cambridge School of Weston, and Professor Jerrold R. Zacharias, MIT. Funded by the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, the National Science Foundation, and the Ford Foundation. Produced by Educational Resources Inc. for the Physical Science Study Committee as part of their course in physics.
  - Deflecting Forces, 1958; Sound, Black & white, 29 minutes. (Reel AV 1991)
    An educational film about deflecting forces funded by the Natioanl Science Foundation, Alfred P. Sloan Foundation and Ford Foundation as part of its course in physics for secondary schools with experimental demonstrations by Nathaniel H. Frank, Chairman of Department of Physics, MIT. Copyright 1958, Educational Services Inc.
  - Dr. Vrick (New York University), c. 1958; Sound, Black & white, 25 minutes. (Reel AV 1793)
    An education professor from Texas speaks about current issues in US schools, comparing with systems in Russia and evaluating data from the past 15 years.
  - Education in Eskimo, Sound, Color, 23 minutes. (Reel AV 1792)
    A documentary about bi-lingual education in Eskimo communities in Alaska. The title in Eskimo is Elitnaureyaraq Yupigtun. Produced by the US Department of the Interior, Juneau Area Office.
  - Elastic Collisions and Stored Energy, 1961; Sound, Black & white, 28 minutes. (Reel AV 1807)
    An educational short film featuring Dr. James S. Strickland of the Physical Science Study Committee. Funded by the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, the National Science Foundation, and the Ford Foundation; produced by Educational Resources Inc. as part of their course in physics.
  - Electronic Residence: TAGER 1968, Sound, Color, 15 minutes. (Reel AV 1953)
    Demonstration of the TAGER system, a closed-circuit educational television program designed to share resources and professors at the university level. Designed by a consortium of Texas universities, including Austin College, Texas Christian University, University of Dallas, and others, the TAGER system formed to unify research and education resources for advanced study, at the graduate level and beyond.
  - Der Heimliche Schrittmacher, Silent, Color, 45 minutes. (Reel AV 1969)
    A short film from the German series "Alternativen", about the Ford Foundation work in impoverished urban areas. Homeless shelters and programs to help addicts are shown, as well as administrative planning and the new Ford Foundation headquarters in Manhattan. Brief graphic footage of monkeys being inoculated.
  - Elementary Charges and Transfers of Kinetic Energy, 1960; Sound, Black & white, 33 minutes. (Reel AV 1959)
    An educational film presented by the Physical Science Study Committee as part of its course in physics, with Dr. Francis L. Friedman of MIT. Funded by the National Science Foundation, Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, and the Ford Foundation. Copyright 1960, Educational Services Inc.
  - Elliptic Orbits, 1959; Sound, Black & white, 19 minutes. (Reel AV 1425)
    An educational short film produced by Educational Resources Inc. as part of their course in physics for secondary school systems. With Dr. Albert V. Baez.
  - The Empirical Formula of a Compound, 1958; Sound, Color, 30 minutes. (Reel AV 1786)
    Episode #14 from an educational series "Chemistry: An Introductory Course", taught by Dr. John F. Baxler from the University of Florida. Produced by Encyclopedia Britannica.
  - Energy and Work, 1959; Sound, Black & white, 30 minutes. (Reel AV 1801)
    An educational short film produced by Educational Resources Inc. as part of their course in physics for secondary school systems. With Professor Dorothy Montgomery, chairman of the Department of Physics, Hollins College.
  - Erie Environment, 1976; Sound, Color, 19 minutes. (Reel AV 2185, Reel AV 1840, Reel AV 2219A, Reel AV 2219B, Reel AV 2219C)
    Short film about environmental management in Erie County, NY. Local officers and citizens worked with the State Department of Environmental Resources, the Department of Sanitation, and the Department of Health to improve water quality and environmental management. Local, ground-level efforts are shown to be more effective than centralized government programs. Produced by John Karol and Apertura, in cooperation with the Erie County Department of Health. Copyright 1976, the Ford Foundation.
  - Experiment on Elasticity, air date: 1958 November 11; Sound, soundtrack only, 30 minutes. (Reel AV 1854)
    Soundtrack to Continental Classrooms, show #45.
  - Experiment on Elasticity, air date: 1958 November 11; Sound, soundtrack only, 30 minutes. (Reel AV 1426)
  - Experiment on Elasticity, air date: 1958 November 11; Sound, soundtrack only, 30 minutes. (Reel AV 1850)
  - Exploratorium, 1975; Sound, Color, 15 minutes. (Reel AV 1855)
    Film about the Exploratorium Science Museum in San Francisco, CA. Interactive exhibits about light, sound, energy, and other natural phenomena are shown, using optical illusions, kinetic artworks, displays of frequency and pitch, and other methods. The end of the film shows the museum founder, Dr. Frank Oppenheimer, discussing the impact of the exhibits with the staff. This film was shot by Jon Boorstin and funded by the National Education Association and the National Science Foundation. Copyright 1975, Jon Boorstin and the Exploratorium.
  - For Fair Play, Sound, Black and White, 28 minutes. (Reel AV 2195)
    Presented by the Pennsylvania State Commission on Industrial this film is a dramatization of desegregation in Bellefonte, Pennsylvania. It is from a white male prepective and he tries to imagine how hard it would be to get a job based on skin color.
  - Ford Foundation Talk, Silent, Black & white, 10 minutes. (Reel AV 2192)
    Negative print of a man being interviewed. Possible H. Rowan Gaither interview.
  - The Fragile Mountain, 1982; Sound, Color, 60 minutes. (Reel AV 1812, Reel AV 1804, Reel AV 2212)
    A 2-part documentary about climate change in the Himalayas, and the effects of environmental shifts on populations and governments. Focuses on Nepal, India, and surrounding nations, showing discussions with villagers, eco-friendly farming technologies, new fuel sources, etc. Produced by Sarah Nichols Productions, with funding from the Ford Foundation. Copyright Sandra Nichols Productions, 1982.
    Renewable energy sources -- Developing countries; Renewable natural resources
  - Franklin Thomas: Guild Hall lecture, Silent, Color, 35 minutes. (Reel AV 1979)
    Franklin Thomas giving a lecture at Guild Hall.
  - Gaither and the Ford Foundation Interview, Sound, Black & white, multiple reels of varying lengths. (Reel AV 2225)
    Unedited footage and audio from an interview with H. Rowan Gaither.
  - Goan Sathis, Sound, Color, 45 minutes. (Reel AV 2223, Reel AV 2203, Reel AV 2207, Reel AV 1999)
    Film about village life in Allahabad, India and the Gaon Sathis who help improve quality of life in these farming communities with new irrigation methods, agricultural techniques, sanitation and writing.
  - Gasoline Engine (The Otto Cycle), 1951; Sound, Black & white, 5 minutes. (Reel AV 1879)
    Short lesson from the College Physics series produced by McGraw-Hill Text Films. Copyright 1951, McGraw-Hill Book Company.
  - The Great Ideas, 1960s; Sound, Black & white, 30 minutes (each episode). (Reel AV 1810, Reel AV 1809, Reel AV 1783, Reel AV 1782)
    Episodes from the TV series featuring Dr. Mortimer J. Adler, director of the Institute for Philosophical Research, in San Francisco. The doctor explains various aspects of philosophy and responds to viewer questions. Directed by Jim Baker, produced by George Bryson and KGO-TV, San Francisco.
  - Harvest of Energy, Sound, Color, 26 minutes. (Reel AV 1977)
    Study of the biological, social, and environmental effects of rice in the human diet. Includes the production of new varieties, transplant techniques, testing of herbicides, water management, traditional methodologies, and other related criteria.
  - The Haven, Sound, Black & white, 16 minutes (Reel AV 1848)
    Short documentary about the emigration of refugee Kalmyk people from Soviet Russia into the United States. Supported by US Government agencies and the Church World Service, a religious group, families were transferred from disparate camps throughout Europe to new settlements in the United States; communities in Philadelphia and New Jersey are profiled in detail. Presented by the United States Information Service, produced by Thomas Craven Film Productions.
  - Hoffman On Tour, Sound, Black & white, 13 minutes. (Reel AV 1951, Box 2, Dvd AV 1951)
    A promotional film about a world-wide trip by Ford Foundation president Paul Hoffman. Ford administrators traveled the world looking for projects and causes to support. Footage of Mr. Hoffman in India and Hong Kong, and Dr. Robert Hutchins in Berlin. Hoffman speaks of supporting peace, local leadership and combating the rise of Communism.
  - Housing: A Place to Live, 1973; Sound, Color, 60 minutes. (Reel AV 1871)
    A 2-part documentary about issues of housing, taxes, and inequality in the NY region, including NYC and parts of NJ and CT. This episode is the first in a series of "televised town meetings" designed to face issues within the area and encourage civic dialogue. The series, "Choices for 76", was timed to address challenges and solutions in preparation for the Bicentennial of the USA. The series was presented by the Regional Plan Association in the spring of 1973, which published an accompany text entitled "How to Save Urban America", as well as other newspaper and print articles. Produced by David Sawyer and Albert Waller, in collaboration with the US Department of Housing and Urban Development. Funded by a variety of institutions, including the Ford Foundation, Rockefeller Brothers Fund, the Taconic Foundation and Rockefeller Foundation.
  - Human Reproduction, 1947; Sound, Black & white, 19 minutes. (Reel AV 1955)
    A short film explaining the reproductive system and process of birth, through diagrams and illustrations. Correlates to the textbook "Healthful Living" by Dr. Harold S. Diehl. Produced by Audio Productions Inc for the McGraw-Hill Health Education Series. Copyright 1947, McGraw-Hill Book Company.
  - IFA: Yoruba Divination and Sacrifice, Sound, Black & white, 13 minutes. (Reel AV 1803)
    An examination of Ifa beliefs within Nigerian communities, which honor water, natural elements, and ancestral spirits. Footage of group prayers, animal sacrifice, and consultation of the natural spirits. Directed by Raymond Price, M.D., of the Section of Transcultural Psychiatric Studies at McGill University. Funded by the Human Ecology Fund, New York.
  - I Just Wanted to Let You Know How Well Rhonda is Doing in School, 1966; Sound, Black & white, 40 minutes. (Reel AV 1962)
    Documentation of a 5-year study involving 18 schools throughout California attempting new teaching and administrative methods.
  - The Imprisonment of Obatala, Sound, Color, 8 minutes. (Reel AV 1876)
    A stop-motion film made by children at the New School in Roxbury, CT, as part of the African Art and Culture project. From the Education and Development Center funded by the Ford Foundation.
  - India Awakes, 1956; Sound, Color, 14 minutes. (Reel AV 2224, Reel AV 1776)
    Film documenting the programs and initiatives developed by the Indian government to improve agriculture, education, health, and general wellbeing throughout the villages and towns of India. Depicts crop research, pest prevention, vaccination, state-run training programs in medicine and farming, and other subjects. Presented by the Ministry of India, Department of Food and Agriculture, produced by the Ford Foundation.
  - Indian Rights, Indian Laws, 1978; Sound, Color, 60 minutes. (Reel AV 1922)
    Interviews with Native Americans who are fighting to preserve their history and protect their rights. The documentary follows the political struggles borne by Indian communities across the US. Funded by the Ford Foundation, copyright 1978.
  - Indonesia, 1958; Sound, Black & white, 70 minutes. (Reel AV 2193A, Reel AV 2193C, Reel AV 2193B)
    Lecture 3 of the 15 part "A Changing World in the Light of History" series. Led by Arnold J. Toynbee and presented at Washington and Lee University in Lexington, Virginia. The lecture discusses the history, geography, language, relgion, colonialism, economy, government and current affairs of Indonesia. There is a supplemental question and answer session with the audience after the presentation. Copyright 1958, Encyclopedia Britannica Films, Inc.
  - Inertial Carts, 1959; Sound, Black & white, 12 minutes. (Reel AV 1897)
    An educational short film featuring Dr. Albert P. Little. Presented by the Physical Science Study Committee, copyright 1959, Educational Services Inc.
  - Inertial Mass, 1959; Sound, Black & white, 19 minutes. (Reel AV 2213, Reel AV 1849)
  - Investment in Human Progress, Sound, Black & white, 42 minutez. (Reel AV 2221, Reel AV 1997 A/B)
    An introductory history of the Ford Foundation, its trustees and programs during the 1950s given by Henry Ford II and H. Rowan Gaither. Henry Ford II introduces the board of trustees- Frank W. Abrams, James F. Brownlee, John Cowles, Donald K. David, Mark F. Ethridge, Laurence M. Gould, John J. McCloy, Charles Wilson, Charles E. Wyzanski, Jr., H. Rowan Gaither, Jr. and Benson Ford. Clips of "Goan Sathis", "Kennan on Communism" and "Community Leadership Institute" are used as examples of the types of work being done at the Ford Foundation.
  - In Service Training, 1962-1963; Sound, Black & white (negative only), 60 minutes. (Reel AV 1963)
    An introductory film about educational television programming for elementary schools. Discussions with a panel of educators planning for their school year
  - Kennan on Communism, 1953; Sound, Black & white, 43 minutes. (Reel AV 1990)
    George F. Kennan discusses communism on the Armed Forces Forum in a question and answer session with servicemen. The Q&A is moderated by Frank Blair. Produced and distributed by the United States Army.
  - LAT & TCP Excerpts, Sound, Black & white, 10 minutes. (Reel AV 1423)
    Related Materials
    See: AV 1856.
    Unedited reel of footage examining teacher training, peer tutoring and learning exercises, edited for 1974 Foundation Board meeting.
  - Learning About Thinking and Vice Versa, 1971; Sound, Black & white, 34 minutes. (Reel AV 2188, Reel AV 2204, Reel AV 1970A, Reel AV 1970B, Reel AV 2189)
    Children's thinking processes are demonstrated by educator Eleanor Duckworth through classic Piaget-type interviews held during a workshop for teachers, teacher aides, and principals of two inner-city Philadelphia schools. Developed primarily for teachers and others who deal with children, the film is intended to help deepen understanding of developmental differences in learning. Copyright Ford Foundation, 1971.
  - Lessons of Sukhmanjri, 1979; Sound, Color, 10 minutes. (Reel AV 1884)
    Film about the efforts of the Indian Council of Agricultural Research to aid rural farmers. New methods of irrigation and crop management are presented as tools of stabilizing the country. Produced by the Films Division of the Indian Government, copyright 1979.
  - Let's Sing Together, Sound, Color, 55 minues. (Reel AV 1911)
    An American student group travels to Hungary to study the Kodaly Music training curriculum, along with their teachers and parents. Filmed at the International Studios of Mafium in Budapest and other locations, the film shows the group interacting with Hungarian teachers and students to study and play music together.
  - Light, Sound, Color, 9 minutes. (Reel AV 2005, Reel AV 1996)
    Art film about light and its influence in different environments. Photographed and direct by Manfred Kirchheimer., and produced by Roemer-Young Associates.
  - Living Commitment, 1974; Sound, Color, 21 minutes. (Reel AV 1870)
    Urban documentary that examines interracial communities and projects throughout the United States, including neighborhood associations in Brooklyn, Connecticut, Los Angeles, and Baltimore. Copyright 1974, National Neighbors.
  - Long Time Intervals, 1960; Sound, Black & white, 30 minutes. (Reel AV 1790)
    An educational film presented by the Physical Science Study Committee, funded by the National Science Foundation, the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, and the Ford Foundation. Featuring Professors Harrison Brown, Charles P. McKinney, and Leon T. Silver from the California Institute of Technology. Produced by Educational Services, Inc.
  - A Magnet Laboratory, Sound, Black & white, 21 minutes. (Reel AV 1994)
    An educational film about electromagnetic force funded by the Natioanl Science Foundation, Alfred P. Sloan Foundation and Ford Foundation as part of its course in physics for secondary schools with experimental demonstrations by Professor Francis Bitter, MIT, Dr. John F. Waymouth, Slyvania Electric Products Inc., Evangel Bardho, MIT and Henry H. Kolm Lincoln Laboratories. Produced by Educational Services Incorpated Film Division and Directed by Richard Leacock.
  - The Man in the Middle, 1968; Sound, Black & white, 22 minutes. (Reel AV 1894)
    Documentary produced by the New York Police Academy with the John Jay College of Criminal Justice, to demonstrate issues and suggestions for preventing violence and social disruption. Shows real police working in Queens, NY, answering domestic calls and integrating with the community in order to build trust. "Public demonstration is a legal means of affecting social change, speak out". Funded by the Ford Foundation. Copyright 1968, John Jay College.
  - Measurement of the Speed of Light, 1952; Sound, Black & white, 5 minutes. (Reel AV 1875)
    Brief educational film from McGraw-Hill Company explaining methods of measuring the speed of light. Diagrams illustrate lessons from Foucault and Michelson. Produced in collaboration with the Visual Aids Committee of the American Association of Physics Teachers. Copyright 1952, McGraw-Hill Book Company.
  - Measuring Large Distances, 1959; Sound, Black & white, 30 minues. (Reel AV 1789)
    An educational film presented by the Physical Science Study Committee, as part of its course on physics for secondary schools. With Professor Fletcher G. Watson of Harvard University. Produced by Educational Services Inc.
  - Measuring Small Distances, 1953; Sound, Black & white, 20 minutes. (Reel AV 1964)
    An educational film presented by the Physical Science Study Committee, as part of its course on physics for secondary schools. With Professor Dorothy Montgomery of Hollins College, Virginia. Produced by Encyclopedia Brittanica. Copyright, Educational Services Inc.
  - Medbourne Primary School, 1969; Sound, Black & white, 11 minutes. (Reel AV 2012, Reel AV 1887, Reel AV 1888)
    A visit to a nontraditional primary school in England that uses innovative programs to support independent development and student leadership. Typical curriculum is replaced with hands-on projects, self-led lessons, outdoors activities, and other innovative methods to empower students. Produced by Henry Felt, in cooperation with the Educational Development Center. Funding from the Public Education of the Ford Foundation.
  - Meeting of the Advisory Committee, Silent, Black & white, 4 minutes. (Reel AV 1420)
    Unedited silent footage from an undated meeting of a Ford Foundation Committee. Various unidentified talking heads are shown.
  - Movement, Sound, Color, 9 minutes. (Reel AV 1874)
    Brief science film explaining the physics of movement, presented by the American Federation of Arts. Produced by ACI, funded by the Ford Foundation.
  - Movement, Silent, Color, 12 minutes. (Reel AV 1874, Reel AV 2003, Reel AV 1896)
    Seemingly stock footage of motion and movement in nature, architecture, technology, and fine art: leaves in the wind, rushing water, children running and playing, machines in factories, and depictions of movement in paintings and sculptures. From Roehmer, Young & Associates.